[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-seven]
[第二十七集]
Xingang
心刚
LaoGuo
老郭
Xingang, what's wrong with you.
心刚你怎么了
Xingang, say something, please.
心刚 你说句话你
You are frightening me.
你
Xingang, Xingang, say something
心刚心刚你说说话
Don't scare me.
你别吓我
this
这
What happened to your hair?
你头发怎么了
Xingang
心刚
XingangXingangXingang
心刚心刚心刚
Xingang, say something.
心刚你说话呀
Let's go.
咱们走
Come on, Xingang, let's not stay here.
走心刚咱们别在这儿待着
go
走
Let's go.
咱们走
Come and get up.
来起来
Come
来
Let's go find Mr. Zhongfu. Let's go.
走咱们去找仲甫先生 走
Let's go find Mr. Zhongfu.
走咱们去找仲甫先生啊
Xingang
心刚
Brother Zhongfu writes well.
仲甫兄写得好啊
Every sentence hit my heart.
句句都写到我心坎里去了
If we want to really change a country,
想要真正改变 变一个国家
We can't do it alone.
单靠我们是不行的
Exactly
没错
Zhongfu
仲甫
Mr. Zhongfu
仲甫先生
Come in
快进来
What's the matter here?
怎么了这是
Xingang is sick.
心刚病了
Why is your hair all white?
头发怎么都白了
What happened?
怎么了这是
Xingang, he was stimulated by the Paris Peace Conference.
心刚他受了巴黎和会的刺激
He was utterly frustrated.
想不开
Sat by the river in the wild all night.
自己在野外河边坐了一晚上
It's probably a cold.
估计是受了寒
Caused him passing out.
一下子昏倒了
I'm gonna make him some brown sugar water.
我赶紧去给他弄点红糖水
Right away.
马上就来
XingangXingang
心刚心刚
you
你
Why you have to bear all those in your mind?
你说你怎么心思就这么重呢
Tell us what's the problem.
你有什么心结你说出来
We can work together.
大伙可以想办法呀
Sir
先生
Sir, I'm fine.
先生我没事
I just haven't been able to sleep these days.
我就是这两天 一直睡不着觉
I can see my father as soon as I close my eyes.
一闭上眼 我就能看到我父亲
My father
我父亲
He was the General Commander of Dengzhou in Qing Dynasty.
原来是清朝登州总兵
Under Gaoyuan Zhang's administration.
章高元手下的将领
In 1897
一八九七年
German East Asia Fleet Commander
德国东亚舰队司令
Dietrich attacked Qingdao.
狄特立克斯攻打青岛
My father was in Jimo County.
我父亲在即墨县城
He fought against them.
跟他们千了一仗
Later, he was dismissed and returned home.
后来被革职回乡
It wasn't long before my father died of illness.
没过多久 父亲就病逝了
Before he passed away,
临死前
He called me to his side and told me.
文亲把我叫到身边跟我说
Xingang, the lost of Qingdao was on me.
心刚 青岛是在我手上弄丢的
When we have Qingdao back one day,
什么时候青岛收回来了
You must tell me.
你一定要告诉我
Sir, Xingang just doesn't understand.
先生 心刚不明白呀
Didn't we win?
我们不是打赢了吗
Germany defeated
德国打败了
Qingdao should be returned to us.
青岛该收回来了
I wanted to tell my father at his grave.
我本来想到父亲的坟前跟他说
Father,
你看
Qingdao is back now.
现在青岛收回来了
Qingdao is back.
青岛收回来了
But now what's going on?
可现在这是怎么了
The last thing my father said before he left was
父亲临走前说的最后一段话是
Lu You's poem "Shi Er"
陆游的《示儿》
That after death everything becomes void, I surely perceive.
死去元知方事空
Yet, not to have seen my country unified is still what makes me grieve.
但悲不见九州同
The day comes when our troops take back the old land.
王师北定中原
Forget not to tell me when you remember me at my grave.
家祭无忘告乃翁
Xingang, being sad can't help right now.
心刚 光难过没有用
You must have stayed up the whole night.
昨夜你在野外一定没睡
I also had a sleepless night.
我也一夜无眠
I wrote three articles.
写了三篇文章
Bai Lan, read this for everyone.
白兰 把这篇给大家读读
Paris peace conference
巴黎的和会
All countries focus on their own interests.
各国都重在本国利益
What justice? What permanent peace?
什么公理什么永久和平
What's President Wilson's Fourteen Declarations?
什么威尔逊总统的十四条宣言
All has become a worthless empty talk.
都成了一文不值的空话
France, Italy and Japan are three militaristic countries.
那法意日本三个军国主义国家
Because it didn't meet with their desire to invade other land.
因为不称他们侵略王地的野心
They threw a tantrum, put on a show and threatened to quit the peace meeting.
动鞭就要大发脾气 退出和会
I say this meeting is all about share the spoils.
我看这个分赃大会
Was it about permanent peace with the world?
与世界永久和平
True happiness of mankind?
人类真正幸福
It's thousands of miles apart.
隔得不正十方八千里
It has to be people all over the world stand together,
全世界的人民都站起来
that this can be solved directly.
直接解决不可
If you count on this share dividing meeting
若是靠着分赃会议
Those politicians and diplomats
那几个政治家 外交家
All they do is keep the door shut and play it dirty.
在那里关门弄鬼
There can't be fair outcomes.
定然没有好果
Sir, you mean
先生的意思是
that we cannot rely on others,
光靠别人是靠不住的
that we people must stand up,
必须要人民自己站起来
and do it ourselves.
直接解决不可
Yes, you are right.
就是这个意思
Xingang, we are at this point already.
心刚 事情已经出了
At this time,
在这个时候呢
it's no use being sad.
难过 悲观都没有什么用处
The imperialist government is unreliable.
帝国主义的政府是靠不住的
China's feudal government is also unreliable.
中国的封建政府也靠不住
What is reliable then?
什么靠得住呢
Ourselves
我们自己
At time like this.
这个时候
We have to and should stand up.
我们只能而且应该站出来
With our own strength.
用我们自己的力量
Save our own country.
拯救我们自己的国家
Sir, tell us.
先生 您说
What should we do now?
我们现在该怎么做
Go into action
行动起来
Resolutely resist that shameless peace treaty
坚决抵制 那个无耻的和约
We will never let the Beiyang government
绝不能让北洋政府
sign that ridiculous peace treaty.
在那个荒唐的和约上签字
We must fight like your father.
我们要像你父亲一样去抗争
You have to believe,
你要坚信
through our efforts,
通过我们的努力
your father's last wish，
你父亲的遗愿
It will come true one day.
总有一天会实现
Sir.
先生
I follow you.
我听你们的
Gentlemen, I'll follow you too.
二位先生 我也跟着你们
Good.
好
Xingang, now drink the brown sugar water.
心刚 把红糖水喝了
The President arrived.
大总统到
Bo Tang, I heard that
伯棠 听说
The opinions of your foreign affairs committee have come out.
你们外交委员会的意见出来了
Tell me about it.
说说吧
Lu Zhengxiang is sending several telegrams in one day, asking for it.
陆征祥一天好几个电报催着呢
So, everyone signed this, that's serious.
这么正式 每个人都签了名
Sit down.
坐吧
We are under the pressure of being called traitor,
担看卖国贼的干系
Dare not handle this without certain seriousness
不敢不认真
Tell me more.
你具体说说吧
At the end of the day, it's just two words, no signing.
其实就两个字 拒签
Refuse to sign.
拒签
Is it easy to say, have you considered the consequences?
说得容易 考虑到后果了吗
We discussed it for two days.
我们商量了两天
All the consequences have been considered.
什么后果都考虑过了
But a telegram from Lu Zhengxiang said
可是陆征祥来电报说
If we don't sign the peace treaty
如果我们不签和约
At least Japan, Britain, France and Italy,
至少日本 英国 法国
these four countries
意大利四国
will challenge us.
将会对我们发难
If that happens,
那样的话
what we lost,
我们丢掉的
it's not just Germany's rights and interests in Shandong,
就不仅仅是德国在山东的权益
but the rights and interests of the whole country.
而是整个国家的权益
That kind of loss is too big.
那损失就大了
We might be the country won the war,
我们这个战胜国
but we would end up with nothing.
将真正成为一无所得呀
Have you considered this?
这一点你们考虑过了吗
Lu Zhengxiang has never
陆征祥从来没有
told me about this problem.
跟我说过这个问题
But he's telling me that every day.
可是他天天跟我这么说
What does Lu Zhengxiang want?
陆征祥是什么意思
It's very clear.
他的意思很清楚啊
He thinks we should sign the treaty.
他主张签字
So as not to lose big over small issue.
以免因小失大
Lu Zhengxiang cannot see the bigger picture and not following his order.
陆征祥鼠目寸光 阳奉阴违
He should be held accountable just for suggesting put this country and its people into disaster.
祸国殃民 当千刀方剐
Botang, what are you talking about now.
伯棠 你这是千仟么呢
Isn't this a discussion?
大家这不是在商量吗
Calm down.
你这
President Xu
徐大总统
Premier Qian
钱总理
Open your eyes.
你们开眼睛看看
If Republic of China,
中华民国
if this government signs this peace treaty,
要是在这个和约上签了字
do you dare to step out of the gate of the Presidential Palaceever again?
你们还敢迈出总统府这个大门吗
Brother Botang
伯棠兄
That sounds almost horrifying.
危言箕听了
Now I need you to answer Lu Zhengxiang's question.
现在需要你回答陆征祥的问题
Sign and not sign
签字与不签字
Which option
究竟哪个
will lead to greater loss of this country's interests?
对我们国家的权益损失更大
Lu Zhengxiang is simply a worrywart.
陆征祥纯粹是杞人忧天
He's talking nonsense.
胡说八道
All the spearheads of the Paris Peace Conference
巴黎和会的所有矛头
they all aim at Germany.
针对的都是德压
The Versailles system will tear Germany to pieces.
凡尔赛体系必定把德国撕得粉碎
How can Germany then bargain with China?
它怎么能够和中国讨价还价呢
Anyone with diplomatic common sense
但凡有外交常识的人
will not raise this kind of question.
也不会提出这个问题
Sit.
坐
According to what you say,
照你这么说
Lu Zhengxiang is worrying too much.
是陆征祥多虑了
This is not a problem at all.
这根本就不是一个问题
Premier Qian
钱总理
I
我
I really want to hear your opinion.
很想听到你的意见
I will listen to the president.
全听大总统的
Sit down
坐下
Acting Chief Chen, what's your opinion?
陈代理总长 你的意见呢
I am a member of the Foreign Affairs Committee.
我是外交委员会的成员
I already signed the message of refusal.
已经在拒签的电文里签了名
President.
大总统
This is what we have drawn up.
这是我们拟定的
A Telegram to the Chinese delegation, refusal to sign.
给中国专使的拒签电令
Please take a look, President.
请大总统过自
What's your opinion?
大家的意见呢
Refuse to sign
拒签
Since everyone agrees we should not sign.
既然大家都认为可以拒签
Then please Premier Qian,
那就请钱总理
send it in the name of the State Council.
以国务院的名义发出吧
But this matter must be kept secret.
但是这件事情一定要保密
The young people can't know.
不能让那些娃娃们知道
Yes, President.
是 大总统
You go to the telecommunications office right now.
你去电讯处
Send a telegram to Lu Zhengxiang immediately.
立刻给陆征祥发电
It's still dark in Paris.
现在 巴黎那边天还没亮呢
Right now
就现在
I want to lambaste Lu Zhengxiang.
我要痛骂陆征祥
This treacherous clown.
这个阳奉阴违的小人
Why does he advocate for signing the treaty?
他为什么主张签约
You don't need to send a telegram for that matter.
要是因为这事您不用发电报了
I can tell you the truth.
我能告诉您真相
What truth?
什么真相
So,
你知道
Lu Zhengxiang never once said he agree to sign the treaty.
陆征祥根本没提出要签约
Duan Qirui asked him to analyze the current situation.
是段祺瑞让他详细分析一下
How Europe and America, including Germany
欧美各国包括德压
how will they react to the Shandong issue.
对山东问题的态度
In Lu Zhengxiang's long analysis report,
陆征祥的长篇分析报告中
there's one paragraph about Germany.
有一段是关于德国的分析
Duan Qirui, underlined that alone.
段祺瑞把它单独摘出来
and commented with eight words.
并批了八个字
Not worthy losing even more over small matter.
因小失大 得不偿失
Cao Rulin presented that to Xu Shichang,
曹汝霖以此为据去找徐世昌
said that Lu Zhengxiang's attitude
说陆征祥认为
is that we should sign the treaty for the long-term benefit.
从长远利益着想主张签约
How do you know all those details?
你怎么知道得这么详细
Lin Changmin came just now.
刚才林长民来了
You were not here.
您不在
He asked me to tell you all those.
他让我转告给您
I see.
我说呢
No wonder Xu Shichang behaved weirdly.
这个徐世昌样子怪怪的
He wanted to use me as an excuse to cope Duan Qirui.
原来是想拿我去塘塞段祺瑞
This old fox.
这个老奸巨的家伙
Did Xu Shichang agree to the refusal message?
那徐世昌同意拒签了吗
Barely, but he did.
DIUN
He has asked Qian Nengxun, in the name of the State Council,
已经交给钱能训以国务院的名义
issue a telegram to convey the refusal.
发出拒签专电
Great
太好了
Now you can have a good sleep.
这下您可以好好睡一觉了
I'm still not at ease.
我还是不放心哪
Go to the telecommunications office immediately.
你立刻去电讯处
In my name
以我的名义
Send an urgent telegram to Lu Zhengxiang.
给陆征祥发一个加急电报
Take note of the telegram.
你记一下电文
Stupid one might be,
再愚蠢的人
One shall not make the same mistake again.
也不能犯两次同样的错误
Chinese people will not allow the second Li Hongzhang.
国人不会容许第二个李鸿章
Indeed.
痛快
I'll send it right away
我马上去发
Tell him to respond as soon as possible.
你让他尽快给我回电
good
好
Shiyan, do you need more glue there?
世炎 你那块儿还要不要点强糊啊
Yeah, after I done with this one.
行等我把这幅写完
good
好
come
来
Classmates
同学们
Mr. Shouchang, Mr. Shouchang
守常先生 守常先生
Yes, sir. Hello, sir
先生好 先生好
Let me tell you three things.
我跟大家讲三个情况
First.
第一个
Wang Daxie called Mr Cai.
汪大给蔡先生打了电话
Said the national government had sent out a fax,
说国民政府已经电令
to the Chinese delegation in Paris,
巴黎的外交使团
about the refusal to sign the peace treaty.
拒签和约
good
好
Second thing is,
第二个情况是
National diplomatic association
国民外交协会
sent a notice.
发来了通知
It is scheduled for May 7th.
定于五月七号
The National Convention in Central Park.
在中央公园举行国民大会
We are to boycott the Paris Peace Treaty.
抵制巴黎和约
Peking University
我们北京大学
along with students from other schools.
和各个学校的学生
We will be the main force in this conference.
要成为这次大会的主力军
And the third is that,
第三个情况
the whole country has taken action.
现在全国都已经行动起来了
Especially Shandong.
尤其是山东
Shanghai
上海
Guangzhou
广州
Through different approaches
都在用不同的形式
all started boycott movement.
抵制运动
Thanks to the New Culture Movement.
多亏新文化运动
It set up two flags of science and democracy.
树起了科学和民主的两面旗帜
So we can break the old world,
我们才可以打破那个旧世界
and get to witness this new one.
看到这个新世界
I remember Mr. Zhongfu
我记得仲甫先生
once said this,
曾经说过一句话
that he would not talk about politics for twenty years.
他说要二十年不谈政治
He shall only concentrate on enlightenment.
他要专心地去搞思想启蒙
Well, now he realized
当然现在他也认识到
that he was biased back then.
当初说这句话有失偏颇了
Given the fact that science and democracy,
因为科学和民主
they are inseparable from politics itself.
本身就离不开政治
Democracy itself is politics.
民主本身就是政治
If we want to talk about science and democracy,
我们要谈科学和民主
then politics will come knocking at the door.
政治就会来找上你
No hide from it.
躲都躲不掉
Think about it, everybody.
大家想一想
Everything happened in Peking University in the last three years.
我们北京大学这三年来的所有事
Which one was not related to politics?
哪一件事离得了政治了
I have a question for all of you.
我想问问大伙
What is democracy?
民主是什么
Democracy means that the people are the masters of their country.
民主 民主就是人民当家做主
Xingang is right
心刚说得对
China belongs to the people.
中国是人民的国家
So of course it is the people take responsibility for it.
所以家就应该人民来当
The people shall make decisions.
主就应该人民来做
This is the proper meaning of the country.
这是国家应有之义
But the Republic of China has been around for eight years.
可是民国已经八年了
I want to ask everyone
我想问问大家
Was there even one thing,
有哪一件事
that we got the power to decide.
是我们人民当家做主的
None.
没有
right
对吧
Last year, Duan Qirui
段祺瑞去年
He signed a secret agreement with Japan.
和日本人签订密约
Did he ask for people's opinions?
他问过人民的意见了吗
No.
没有
Even the Chinese Emissary
甚至连中国的专使
didn't know about such a thing.
都不知道有这么一个密约存在
A total liar.
挂羊头卖狗肉
People was deceived.
欺世盗名
People was fooled.
愚弄民众
So I said
所以我说
This Paris peace conference is bad indeed.
这趟巴黎和会
However, there is another way to look like it.
不光是个坏事
There can be a good aspect.
也是一件好事
How so?
为什么这么说
Because of this Paris Peace Conference
因为这个巴黎和会
Chinese are all awake now.
惊醒了我们全体中国人
If China wants to develop,
中国要想发展
opposition to feudalism and leading new culture is not enough.
不能光反对封建主义
We also need to stand out,
倡导新文化
fight against imperialism,
还要反对帝国主义
defend our own sovereignty.
捍卫我们自己的主权
To achieve these,
要做到这两点
we have to wake people up.
就必须要唤醒民众
Only when the people wake up can China have hope.
民众觉醒了 中国才有希望
So, my fellow students.
所以同学们
Our lecture group on civilian education
我们的平民教育讲演团
needs to get close to the grassroots as soon as possible.
要尽快深入到基层去
Go into the factory.
深入到工厂去
Go into the fields.
深入到田间地头去
All of our groups
我们的各个社团
needs to reach out to every corner of society.
要深入到社会的各个角落
To awaken the people.
去唤醒民众
What do you think?
大家觉得怎么样
sir
先生
We are now working on establish a union.
我们现在正在筹备成立
A student union for all tertiary education insititutes in Beijing.
北京中等以上学校学生联合会
We will connect all the schools,
把所有学校都串联起来
make it easier for organizing large-scale activities.
方便组织大规模的活动
Our public education lecture group
咱们平民教育讲演团
will be divided into four smaller teams.
淮备分为四支小队
We are giving a series of speeches in Changxindian and other places respectively.
分别到长辛店等地搞系列演讲
We are organizing a parade right now.
我们正在准备
At the National Assembly on May 7th,
五月七号的国民大会
there will be a parade of 100,000 people.
计划来一个十万人大游行
Good
好
Students
同学们
Let's act now.
那我们现在行动起来
Yes!
好好
Dry up this.
干起来
Government has made it clear,
国民政府已经明令陆征祥
Lu Zhenxiang will refuse to sign the peace treaty.
拒绝在和约上签字
So, for all the speech at this National Assembly
所以这次国民大会的发言
Be sure to pay attention to discretion.
一定要注意分寸
There must be no voice to denounce the government.
绝不能出现声讨政府的声音
Chairman of the committee.
委员长
One important thing.
还有一点更重要
That is, it can never appear
那就是绝不能够出现
the voice of critcizing President Wilson.
辱骂威尔逊总统的声音
Chen Duxiu and Li Dazhao from Peking University,
北京大学的陈独秀和李大钊
in the Weekly Review,
在《每周评论》中
publicly accussed President Wilson being useless.
公开指责威尔逊总统一文不值
We cannot promote this kind of behavior.
这种不顾大局的做法
Endangering the bigger picture.
那不能提倡
We should target the Japanese,
我们要把矛头对准日本人
and the pro-Japanese factions in China.
和国内的亲日派
Cao Rulin,
曹汝霖
Zhang Zongxiang,
章宗祥
and Lu Zongyu.
和陆宗
Chairman of the committee!
委员长
What is it?
什么事
Something bad.
出大事了
Speak.
说
The State Council has secretly sent a message to Paris.
国务院已经密电巴黎专使
They agreed to sign the treaty!
同意签约了
Right, I need to go now.
好先这样吧
How is that possible?
这怎么可能
A guy from Lin Changmin's hometown works in the office.
电报处林长民的一个老乡
He sent that telegram himself.
亲手发的电报
He told Lin Changmin secretly.
他偷偷告诉林长民的
Source is solid.
不会有错
Where is Lin Changmin now?
林长民现在在哪儿
I'll go find him.
我去找他
Lin Changmin just
林长民刚刚
handed Xu Shichang a resignation letter.
给徐世昌打了辞职报告
He asked me to bring you this note.
这是他让我带给您的字条
This government is treacherous.
这个政府背信弃义
I can never go along with it.
我绝不能跟它同流合污
I am resigning too.
我也辞职
Chairman, at this time
委员长 这个时候
You can't just walk away.
您不能一走了之啊
Chairman, Lu Zhengxiang sent a telegram .
委员长 陆征祥电报
Read!
念
Please help me, Brother BoTang.
请佰棠兄救救我
Shameless bustard Xu Shichang!
徐世昌无耻
Shameless bustard Duan Qirui!
段祺瑞无耻
Shameless bustard Qian Nengxun!
钱能训无耻
You send a telegram to Lu Zhengxiang immediately.
你马上给陆征祥发电报
He wants me to save him,
就说 他要我救他
then he must remember my words.
他就要记住我的话
This treaty can never be signed.
这个协议绝不能签
If he signs it,
他要是签了
he will for sure,
那他就成了
be that unforgivable sinner of the Chinese nation, carved in history.
中华民族不可饶恕的千古罪人
I need car.
备车
I'm going to meet Cai Juemin
我要去见蔡子民
You two go there.
你们俩去那儿
You, there.
你去那儿
Yes.
知道啦
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
Chairman Wang has arrived
汪委员长到了
Please come in.
快请
Yes.
好
Jueming.
子民
Brother Botang
伯棠兄
This is devastating.
大事不好了
If we don't do something,
再不想办法
we will not be able to face the future generations.
我们就无颜面对后世子孙了
Brother Botang
伯棠兄
How come?
何以如此
Xu Shichang and Duan Qirui
徐世昌 段祺瑞
These two shamless liar.
背信弃义 出尔反尔
They have sent a telegram to Paris today.
已于今日电令巴黎专使
Agreed to sign the Paris Peace Treaty.
同意签署巴黎和约了
Lu Zhengxiang signed it already?
陆征祥签字了
Not yet.
还没有
He sent me a telegram just now asking me to save him.
他刚才给我发来电报要我救他
I can't save him.
我救不了他
I can't save Shandong.
更救不了山东
Now it's up to the students.
现在只能靠学生们了
Brother Botang, tell me.
伯棠兄 您说
I am only a scholar. What can I do?
我乃一介书生 我能做什么
You can
你能
You, Cai Juemin have Peking University to back you.
你蔡子民有北大
Peking University has China to back it.
北大后面有个中国
When millions of Chinese people stand together for one goal,
四万万中国人只要一条心
then China will not die.
中国就不会亡
Thank you for your advice.
感谢伯棠兄的指点
Yuan Pei knows what to do.
元培自有定夺
The reason why I called everyone together urgently,
我之所以紧急地把大家招集起来
is to discuss a serious matter,
是有一件天大的事情
with everyone here.
要和大家商量
The Beiyang government has sent a telegram to the delegation in Paris.
北洋政府已经电令巴黎的专使
Agreed to sign the Paris Peace Treaty,
同意签暑巴黎和约
officially hand over Shandong to Japan.
把山东正式移交日本
It is happening.
这个已经成为定局了
That's treason!
那这是公开卖国
Mr Cai, we can't stand by and watch.
蔡先生 我们不能袖手旁观哪
We all know that.
我们都清楚
Patriotism is what Peking University believes in.
爱国是我们北大的宗昌
The nation is facing a matter of life and death,
在国家民族出现大难的时候
We will not just stand by and watch.
我们绝不可能袖手旁观
I told Wang Daxie just now,
刚才我跟汪大说
This country is at the edge of a cliff.
国难当头
Me, Cai Yuanpei will go to hell to save it,
我蔡元培不下地狱
even if no one else will follow.
谁下地狱
Mr Cai, I will go to hell with you.
蔡先生 我跟您一起下地狱
Every man is responsible for the rise and fall of the nation.
天下兴亡 匹夫有责
Our country is in trouble,
国家有难
I will go to hell with you.
我跟着您一同下地狱去
Going to hell won't help right now.
下地狱无济于事
I have thought about this for a long time.
这个问题我想了很久
It was an article by Shouchang that inspired me.
是守常的一篇文章启发了我
He mentioned the Russian October Revolution,
他说俄国的十月革命
it's a victory for the common people.
是庶民的胜利
Those people in Russia used violence to win.
俄我国的庶民用的是暴力
What about us Chinese?
那我们中国的庶氏
Can we use democracy?
用民主行不行
Worth trying.
我看可以试
Our country is the people's country.
我们的国家是人民的国家
The people have the final say in this country's fate.
人民的国家得人民说了算
Now Beiyang government went against public opinion.
现在北洋政府违背民意
Sold out the sovereignty of our country.
出卖我们国家的主权
What should we do?
怎么办
I say there is no other way.
我说别无他法
The only solution is to be practised by the people.
只有让人民站起来直接解决吧
How can people unit and solve it then?
怎么个站起来直接解决
No more sitting back and just watch.
变坐而议 为起而行
We, this Peking University need to be the pioneers in this.
我们北大要做先锋
It's time for people to wake up and take the power.
唤醒广大民众做天下的主人
Let's also give the government a subaltern victory.
咱们也来他一个庶民的胜利
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
Deng Zhongxia, they are organizing the Beijing Students Union.
邓中夏他们正在组织北京学联
I urged them to act quickly.
我催促他们赶快行动起来
This operation should not only involving students.
而且这次行动不应该只学生
Workers, merchants and soldiers,
工人商人 军人
All strata should take action.
各个阶层都要行动起来
The whole society stand together,
全社会的各个阶层都行动起来
that is the action of the common people.
这才是庶民的行动
Only that can force the reactionary government to give in.
才能迫使反动政府让步
I agree with Zhongfu and Shouchang.
我同意仲甫和守常的意见
If Peking University can take the lead,
如果我们北大先带个头
pushing people from all over the country to unite,
把全国的民众都调动起来
that will be the beginning of a brand-new history.
那必将是一个全新的历史的开端
Yes, you are influential among young people.
对 你们在青年人中间
They will listen.
是很有影响力和号召力的
Zhongfu said just now
刚才仲甫说
Let the people stand up and take action.
让人民直接站起来行动
I think this sentence should be our slogan.
这句话我认为应该成为口号
Shout this slogan out.
把这个口号喊出去
A call to arms.
把人民调动起来
You two once said
你们二位曾经说
that we should talk about politics directly and openly.
要直接议论政治
I had doubts and reservations at that time.
当时我还有疑虑和保留
Now it seems like,
现在看来
You are the ones have foresight.
你们深谋远虑
But it's hard to cover every aspects if we move in haste.
但是仓促行动容易顾此失彼呀
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
I know what you mean.
我明白您的意思
I'm going to Changxindian now.
我现在就去一趟长辛店
Tell our worker brothers
把巴黎和会的结果
the result of the Paris Peace Conference.
告诉工人兄弟们
Goo.
好
Mr. Shouchang
守常先生
Be careful.
要注意安全
Yucai, come
来豫才
Let's work it out,
我们来商量一下
how to carry out this operation.
这次这个行动
What steps and actions should we take.
我们到底应该怎么样具体地来做
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
Please sit down, teachers and students.
请老师和同学们坐下
Today, I summoned teachers and student representatives together in a hurry.
今天把各位老师和学生代表
I had to.
紧急地招集起来
Beacuse this is urgent matter.
实在是有迫不得已的事情啊
The Paris Peace Conference has now adopted
巴黎和会现在已经通过了一项
this unfair treaty.
不平等的条约
The content of this treaty
条约的内容
Is to remove all the rights
是把战前战败国
of defeated Germany,
德国在中国的所有权益
and to hand it over to Japan.
全部移交给日本
Everyone knows that
大家都知道
we attended this Paris Conference as the victorious country.
中国是作为战胜国的身份
In this conference,
参加这个巴黎和会的
as a defeated one,
在这个和会上
Germany.
作为战败国德国
It should
它理应
return occupied Shandong to China,
把霸占中国山东的土地和权益
give up all rights.
全部无条件地归还给中国
On the contrary, at this peace meeting
然而在这个和会上
big powers ignored China.
他们无视我中国
They even openly came out with a shameless agreement.
堂而皇之地通过了这么一个
This unfair Paris Treaty.
不平等的巴黎和约
Our government
我们现在的政府
has already sent messages to the Chinese delegation in Paris.
已经致电在巴黎的中国代表团
Asked them to
要求他们
sign this shameful peace treaty.
在这个耻辱的和约上签字
We all know,
大家知道
the second they sign this humiliating treaty,
只要这个字一签
Our Shandong
那么我们山东
will go under Japan's control.
就变成日本的了
All students.
同学们
Can we, as a Chinses,
但凡是个中国人
let this happen?
我们能答应吗
No way!
不答应
I came to Peking University three years ago.
三年前我来到北大
I came with a dream in my heart.
我心存着一个梦想
To lead and push Peking University.
要把北大办成一个
To make it an extraordinary insititute for education.
优秀的教育学堂
A university like that,
优秀的教育学堂的背后
it has patriotism written in it's heart.
就准确无误地写上两个字
To love one's country.
爱国
In my opinion.
按我的想法
Patriotism is in future the soul and tradition
爱国今后就是我们北京大学的
of our Peking University.
灵魂和传统
Studying in Peking University,
我北大的学子
is not to be authority,
不是要自己做官
is to contribute to this country.
而是要为国家出力
Be a pillar of this country.
要做国家的栋梁之材
Now our country has arrived
如今国家已经到了
a critical moment of survival.
存亡绝续的关键时刻
Each and every one of our students
我们每一个北大学子
should step forward.
都应该挺身而出
Be a pioneer in saving this country.
为挽救国家的危亡做先锋
We need to call out to the people,
我们要唤起民众
and urge the government,
敦促政府
refusing to sign this unfair Paris peace treaty.
拒签这个不平等的巴黎和约
Defend our sovereignty.
捍卫我们的主权
Students and teachers.
我的同学们老师们
Let me ask you
我问你们
Do you have the courage and strength?
你们有没有这个勇气和力量
We do!
有
Defend sovereignty, no signing the treaty.
捍卫主权 拒签和约
We need people gather here at this intersection.
这个路口人必须集中
Otherwise, we can't have a big enough crowds, understand?
否则形成不了力量 明白吗
What if we can't get enough?
集中了之后 咱们人数达不到
How about here, here, here, here
那这儿这儿这儿
Here?
这儿怎么
How can there be not enough people, it's such a small intersection?
这么小的路口怎么会人数不够
Sir, Brother Ge and more are here
先生 葛师傅他们来了
Mr. Dazhao
大钊先生
Shugui
树贵
I'm grateful to all the workers here for your support.
谢谢各位工友对我们的支持
thank you
谢谢
Mr. Dazhao
大钊先生
Us workers also want to help our country.
我们工人也想为咱们的国家
To do something.
做点事情
Anything you need,
有什么需要我们的
just tell us.
您尽管啊
All right, everybody, have a seat.
好那大伙坐吧
Let's sit and talk.
咱们坐着聊
good
好
Shugui
树贵
So here is the thing.
现在有这么一个情况啊
Our lecture group on civilian education
我们的平民教育讲演团
has set a speech route.
定下来了一个演讲路线
It's marked on the map.
全在地图上
I want you to do me a favor.
我希望你帮个忙
Look at which block has the most workmates.
你看看哪块的工友最多
We'll go there first.
我们就先去哪儿
I see.
我想到时候
I think this place here
咱们的工友在这一块
is where you can find the most workers.
会是最多的
Write it down.
你们记一下
okay
好的
And Mr. Dazhao.
还有 大钊先生
I want to
我到时候想
arrange some workmates
安排一些工友
to keep everything under order with our students.
和咱们的同学一起维持秩序
Students.
同学们
Not long ago.
就在前不久
The Paris Peace Conference has passed one agreement.
巴黎和会已经通过了
An unfair treaty
把我们山东的权益
that our Shandong will be handed over to Japan
交给日本的不平等条约
The moment we sign on this treaty,
只要这个字一签
Shandong will no longer be ours.
山东就是日本的了
Students.
同学们
Can we let this happen?
这种条约我们能答应吗
Never!
不能
No way!
绝不能答应
Exactly, we won't.
对 绝不答应
Look at the uniforms you are wearing.
看看你们身上穿的校服
Look at the emblem of Peking University we are wearing.
看看我们佩戴的北大校徽
Peking University takes patriotism as its soul and tradition.
北大应该以爱国为灵魂和传统
At the critical time of our country's survival,
在我们国家存亡绝续的时候
can we show the world our courage and responsibility?
我们能否拿出这种勇气和担当
Yes!
能
Yeah!
可以
Does anyone want to say something？
刚才的会议
Do you have anything to add?
大家还有什么补充吗
No
没有了
We should spread the words out to other students.
我觉得还需要和其他同学说一下
Okay, that's settled then.
好那就这么定了
May 3rd in the auditorium of Peking University Third Hall.
五月三日在北大三院礼堂
A meeting for all students will be held.
召开全体学生大会
Not only Peking University students,
除开北大学生以列
more than a dozen other schools should be involved,
还要动员其他十几所学校
we need them to send a representative to attend.
派代表参加
Any questions?
各位还有什么问题吗
No
没有了
Then please, everyone.
那就拜托各位
Take action
行动起来吧
Fellow students.
同学们
Here, I declare
下面我宣读
the resolution of Beijing Association of Schools.
北京各学校联合会决议
Firstly, we will unite all classes to strive and to fight.
联各界一致奋起力争
Secondly, the nation humiliation parade scheduled for May 7th
原定五月七日的国耻游行
will now be moved forward to May 4th.
提前于五月四月举行
Thirdly
三
Send messages to the emissary in Paris, no signing.
致电巴黎专使 不准签字
Fourthly
儿
Inform all provinces,
通电各省
On May 7th
五月七日
we are all holding patriotic demonstrations.
律举行爱国示威游行
good
好
Fellow students.
同学们
By the decision of the preparatory group of Student Union.
经学联筹备组决定
We recommend Fu Sinian
大家公推傅斯年同学
as the commander-in-chief of tomorrow's parade.
为明天游行的总指挥
Luo Jialun and ten more others
罗家伦等十余名同学
as the general representative of tomorrow's parade.
为明天游行的总代表
Please cheer for them.
大家欢迎
Yeah
好
Finally, the route map for parade tomorrow
最后 明天大游行的路线图
will be posted at the entrance of the auditorium.
会张贴在礼堂的门口
Please,all school representatives, be sure to read carefully.
请各位学校的代表务必认真阅读
So you can make arrangement and implementation at your school as soon as possible.
尽快带回学校布置落实
Fellow students.
同学们
Down with the traitor, give us back Qingdao!
还我青岛 打倒卖国贼
May 4th, 1919
一九一九年的五月四日
Peking University, Peking teacher's college
北京大学 北京高等师范学校
along with thirteen colleges and technical secondary schools.
等十三所大中专学校的
More than three thousand students from these schools
三千多名学生
gathered at Tiananmen for the parade.
到天安门集会
They made their voices heard.
他们打出
"Fight for sovereignty and punish the traitors sold out this country."
外争主权 内惩国贼
Called for abolishing the 21 Article.
废除二十一条等口号
Strongly demand the denial of Paris Peace Treaty.
强烈要求拒签巴黎和约
Holding three pro-Japanese officials in Beiyang government accountable.
惩办北洋政府三个亲日派官员
Cao Rulin, Zhang Zongxiang
曹汝霖 章宗祥
Lu Zongyu
和陆宗
The parade team was blocked
游行队伍
after they started protesting in the embassy district of Dongjiaominxiang.
在东交民巷使馆区抗议受阻后
They turned to Cao Rulin residence in Zhao Jialou Hutong instead.
转奔位于赵家楼胡同的曹汝霖住宅
Beat up the traitor Zhang Zongxiang
痛打卖国官僚章宗祥
Set Cao's house on fire.
火烧曹宅
May 5th
五月五日
Various schools in Beijing announced that
北京各大中专学校宣布
the teachers and students are going on a strike and call on all parties for support.
实行罢课 并通电各方请求支援
This students' Patriotic Movement in Beijing
北京学生的爱国运动
soon spread out all over the country.
主迅速蔓延到全国各地
May Fourth Movement
晶青科五四运动
It's a great patriotic and revolutionary campaign pioneered by advanced young intellectuals,
五四运动
A great patriotic revolutionary movement resolutely fight imperialism and feudalism.
彻底反帝 反封建的伟大爱国革命运动
A great social revolutionary movement launched by the Chinese people,
是一场中国人民为拯救民族危亡
to save the nation from subjugation, safeguard national dignity
捍卫民族尊严 凝聚民族力量
and pool national strength together.
而起的伟大社会革命运动
A great enlightenment and new cultural movement
是一场传播新思想 新文化
of disseminating new thought, new culture and new knowledge.
新知识的伟大思想启蒙运动
The huge wave from this movement
以磅磺之力
inspired the Chinese people and the Chinese nation,
鼓动了中国人民和中华民族
gave people confidence to achieve the great rejuvenation of the Chinese nation.
实现民族复兴的志和信心
May Fourth Movement
五四运动
With its revolutionary determination in anti-imperialist and anti-feudal,
以彻底反帝 反封建的革命性
the progressiveness of pursuing the truth of saving and strengthening the country,
追求救国 强国真理的进步性
the universality of active participation
各族各界群众
by people from all walks of life,
积极参与的广泛性
It has promoted the progress of Chinese society,
推动了中国社会进步
and the spread of Marxism in China.
促进了马克思主义在中国的传播
Integrated Marxism with the Chinese workers' movement,
同中国工人运动的结合
laid foundation for the establishment of the Communist Party of China.
为中国共产党的成立
Not only ideologically,
做了思想上
but also prepared in human resource level.
干部上的准备
It provided possibility for new revolutionary forces, revolutionary culture and revolutionary battle
为新的革命力量 革命文化 革命斗争
for them to step onto the stage of history.
登上历史舞台创造了条件
It is a turning point where China's old democratic revolution
是中国旧民主主义革命
marching towards the new-democratic revolution.
走向新民主主义革命的转折点
In modern times,
在近代以来
It marked a milestone in the history of Chinese people's pursue
中华民族追求民族独立
for national independence,
和发展进步的历史进程中
and country's development.
具有里程碑意义
Down with the traitor Cao Rulin!
打倒卖国贼曹汝霖
Down with the traitor Zhang Zongxiang！
打倒卖国贼章宗祥
Down with the traitor Lu Zongyu!
打倒卖国贼陆宗
Defend our country!
爱我中华保卫中国
Down with the traitor Zhang Zongxiang
打倒卖国贼章宗祥
LaoGuo, are you alright?
老郭老郭老郭 没事吧
Is Guo okay?
老郭 没事吧
Take him to the hospital now.
快送医院
hurry up
快快快
Guo
老郭
Hang in there.
坚持住啊
Defend our country!
爱我中华
We have to arrest these students.
必须得抓 这帮学生
Students' disturbances must be severely punished.
学生闹事 必须得严惩
You can use the police when necessary.
必要的时候可以动用警察嘛
Right
对吧
Arrest them.
必须得抓
Let me tell you something, these students--
这帮学生我跟你讲
Premier Qian arrives.
钱总理到
I gathered everyone this late at night.
这么晚叫大家来
It's for urgent matter. Please sit down.
也是因为事情紧急 请坐
Today, students from Peking University
今天北京大学
and others from more than a dozen schools marched in the streets.
和十几所学校上街游行
They also burned Zhao Jialou.
并火烧赵家楼
I'm sure you all already know.
想必各位都已经知道了
President Xu is very angry about this matter.
徐大总统对此事十分生气
Ask our cabinet to come up with a plan immediately.
要求我们内阁即刻拿出预案
In case things get worse.
以防事态进一步扩大
General Duan also called.
段大师也打来电话
Require strict control over troubled students.
要求对闹事学生严加管束
Now, please let Cheif of Army Li Changtai
现在请步军统领李长泰
present an introduction to the situation.
把情况向大家做一个介绍
Members of the cabinet
各位阁员
This task of introducing the situation,
介绍情况这个活儿呀
it should be Wu Bingxiang of the Metropolitan Police Department.
应该是京师警察厅吴炳湘的事情
Wu Bingxiang, this old prick, dare not come.
吴炳湘这老滑头不敢来
So, allow me to take over.
让我替他
Things are like this,
那我就跟大家说说啊
From 1: 00 this afternoon
今天下午一时起
More than 3,000 students from more than a dozen schools in Beijing
北京十几所学校三千多学生
started parade on the streets.
开始上街游行
This student nonsense
这次学生闹事
is particularly serious in nature.
性质特别严重
The influence is very bad.
影响非常恶劣
President Xu Shichang has given the order.
徐世昌大总统已经下达
Ban the parade immediately
立即取缔游行
And stop students from making trouble.
和制止学生闹事的命令
He also asked the cabinet
并要求内阁
to make a rapid action plan.
迅速制定行动方案
Prevent something worse from happening tomorrow.
以防止明日闹出更大的事情
Cheif Li has made it clear.
李统领把情况
Let's discuss.
诸位 议议吧
They must be arrested.
抓必须抓起来
Repression.
就是 镇压
Passers-by made the secene worse.
路人弄得这些哨子
It's no good arresting them.
抓捕没用
Here's my view on this.
要我说呀
Students are troublesome indeed,
这学生闹事固然可恶
but what's even worse is those behind it.
但更可恶的是那些幕后指使人
Cai Yuanpei, headmaster of Peking University
北京大学校长蔡元培
And several backbones around him.
和他身边的几个骨干
Like Chen Duxiu and Li Dazhao.
陈独秀 李大钊等人
They are the culprit.
才是罪魁祸首
Should be severely punished.
更应该严惩
This Cai Heqing has done nothing good
这个蔡鹤卿自从执掌北大以来
since he was in charge of Peking University.
他就没有办过一件好事
In my opinion, he must be dismissed.
依我看 必须把他革职
I would like to remind you that
我要提醒诸位
What caused this student parade
学生游行
It was the humiliating Paris Peace Treaty.
起因是那个丧权辱国的巴黎和约
Cai Yuanpei
蔡元培
Is the first education chief of the Republic of China.
是中华民国的首任教育总长
Since he took charge of Peking University
他执掌北大以来
he has won people's favor through a serious of measures.
采取一系列措施 深得人心
If he leaves Peking University
如果让他离开北大
It is bound to lead to greater public grievances.
势必引发更大的民怨
The consequences would be unthinkable.
后果不堪设想
Those people from the Ministry of Education and Cai Yuanpei
教育部那些人和蔡元培
they are all on the same side.
穿的是一条裤子
This mess students made
学生闹事
is the result of your appeasement.
就是你们姑息迁就的结果
This Cai Yuanpei must leave.
这个蔡元培必须罢免
Must be removed
必须罢免
Gentlemen
诸位 诸位 诸位
I think
我以为
Fu, chief of the Ministry of Education, is thinking too much about this.
教育部傅总长有些危言箕听了
You said Cai Yuanpei's position is unshakable.
你说蔡元培的地位不可动摇
What if Cai Yuanpei dies?
那要是蔡元培死了呢
Is Peking University gonna shut down?
北京大学就关门了吗
Premier
总理
But then,
当然了
What we discuss today
我们今天要讨论的
is not about removing Cai Yuanpei.
不是罢免蔡元培的问题
But how to prevent worse situation from happending.
而是如何防止事态进一步扩大
Fundamentally speaking, this matter
这件事从根本上说
is the responsiblity of Ministry of Education
责任在教育部
But we are the Republic of China.
可我们是中华民国
There is laws and regulations.
办事要讲法度
It's students' affairs
学生的事
Of course, it's up to the Ministry of Education.
当然要由教育部来管
Public security matters
治安的事
Of course, the police department is in charge.
当然是警察厅来管
The Chief of Army should take care of army business.
步军统领门是军队
You'd better stay out of this.
最好不要插手此事
So as not to make things getting serious.
免得把事情闹大了
I heard that the students who were caught
我听说被抓来的学生
they are still locked up in army's jail.
到现在还被关在步军统领门
That's against the regulation.
这就不合法度嘛
So, inform Wu Bingxiang.
这样 通知吴炳湘
Tell him to immediately take the captured students
让他即刻把抓来的学生
move them to the police station.
送到警察厅
How interesting.
新鲜啊
I worked all day long on this.
闹了半天
Turns out what I did is wrong.
我这出力还出出毛病了
Fine, I will walk.
行老子不管了
I'm meeting General Duan, reasoning with him.
我找段师说理去
Lao Li
老李
Don't go!
别走啊
Don't go. You can't go
别走啊不能走啊你
Please sit down, everyone.
诸位 诸位 请坐请坐
I discussed it with President Xu.
我和徐大总统商量过了
To deal with this matter,
对付学生闹事
we have to be tough in the action.
我们手段要严厉
But be gentle in the words.
态度要怀柔
The goal is not to make things worse.
自的是不要扩大事态
The most important thing right now is May 7th.
眼下最为重要的是五月七日
The National Convention held in Central Park
在中央公园召开的国民大会
In any case, they cannot be allowed to hold this conference.
无论如何不能让他们开这个大会
This National Convention can't lead to anything good.
这国民大会一开呀
We can't even start to imagine the outcome.
那才是后果不堪设想
Students.
同学们
According to the information from each school
根据各个学校的核实
It has been found out.
现已查明
A total of 32 students were arrested.
我们共有三十二名同学被捕
There are twenty students from Peking University.
其中北大学生二十人
Eight people from teacher's college.
高等师范学校八人
Two people from industrial specialized school.
高等工业专门学校两人
One from Huiwen University and one from University of China.
中国大学 汇文大学各一人
These students now
这些同学
are in the jail under amry department.
被究宪兵带到步军统领衙门
Xu Deheng and other students from Peking University,
我们北大的许德等同学
they are locked up in the standing cage prepared for felons.
还被关在四禁重刑犯的站笼里
Humiliated and tortured.
受尽了凌辱
Word is that
有消息说
Reactionary warlord Duan Qirui
反动军阀段祺瑞
aims at revenge for traitor Cao Rulin.
为了给卖国贼曹汝霖出气
He gave orders to severely punish the arrested students.
已经下令要严惩被捕同学
Their lives are in danger now.
他们现在面临生命危险
The situation is not optimistic.
情况不容乐观
We must not stand by and watch.
我们绝不能袖手旁观
We will not.
绝不能袖手旁观
Must not
绝不能
Please be quiet.
大家请安静
Quiet please
请安静
Mr Cai has arrived.
蔡先生到了